aan I am
perplexed despite my understanding of
the theory and being one of consistent
practice as I believe I seem to lack
lack intellectual
press I believe that acquiring wisdom
would make me quick witted and enable me
to teach others
eloquently what could be the reason for
not attaining such an
ability well have you attained the
ability of wisdom first I've got all the
theory down well that's the
problem so in order to be quick withed
and be able to convey your wisdom to
others you need to have the
wisdom so you need to become an expert
for yourself in other words uh you need
to fully understand the way out of
suffering and the Buddhist teaching and
then you won't have to plan and think
how you can convey that to others
because you will become well vered well
versed in it like the similar in the
sutas when when he asked the Buddha do
you have to prepare the answers
beforehand when people come to you like
do do you have the answers prepared
waiting he says
no uh let me ask you in return and then
you can understand how it is and he says
you are a chariot maker master and says
yes there is nobody that can match my
knowledge of Chariots and how to make
them and how to disassemble them he
knows everything inside out says well if
somebody were to come and ask you about
a chariots would you need to prepare an
answer for it he said no if somebody
were to wake me in the wake me up in the
middle of the night I will give them the
answer because that's how uh fully
understood I am basically he he he he
knows all of it so that's the point now
you have your abstract theoretical
knowledge well you have to start
applying it and you know you're applying
it when you're becoming free from
suffering on account of your
understanding not on account of your
management when suffering can't touch
you to begin with because your mind
doesn't move because the mind understood
the nature of
things and and uh if you're developing
in that regard you will be able to
convey that to others now of course
there is the aspect and that's also
mentioned in the sutas some people are
simply more skilled in teaching some
people are less skilled in teaching but
that's something you can understand only
once you have a thing to
teach so now you can think oh I must be
the type that's not skilled in teaching
well you you might not be that type it's
just the fact that now you have nothing
to teach really so if you develop wisdom
correctly in other words if you free
yourself from suffering correctly then
you'll see how prolific how how how
skilled in teaching you are but what I'm
saying is that even the least skilled
soana is still far more skilled than
anything a putuj I can even
imagine because there is no way that you
would not be able to con convey what you
fully understood this that's simply not how
understood this that's simply not how
things work so if you can't convey it is
you haven't understood it and that's
what y was said in in his letters like
don't think you understood something
unless you can write it down and as we
talked the other day we can actually add
another one and upgrade that statement
don't think you understood something
until you can explain it to somebody
else because you know you can sit down
and write it for three or four hours and
boil it down uh but if you actually try
and tell it to somebody who doesn't have
3 hours to listen to you can you convey
your message can you make the point
and if you can't means there
isn't the width of your understanding is
not sufficient so trying to explain things
sufficient so trying to explain things
even to yourself is is is a useful
practice because if you're just
operating on the mental level of your
thoughts and Theory with like half
expressed phrases and and terms and
Concepts yeah that's just like you can
do that with yourself because you kind
of already know what you're
thinking but if you were to then try and
say that it just comes out completely
different and then it's like oh that's
not what I wanted to say I was like well
that's exactly the
problem you need to have the
understanding that would pertain to all
these layers whether it's the most
abstract your own kind of idiosyncratic
way of revolving around your thoughts
and images down to saying it to somebody
else telling it to
them and that is the measure of
understanding not the idiosyncratic
images that you have and that make you
feel good cuz people think I made
everything I made all of the sense in my
head thus that's my understanding yeah
that certainly helpful and that's the
beginning and you should develop it but
you develop it by actually being able to
utter it and uh uh convey it write it
down clarify it boil it down to a point
because if if if the if understanding is
insufficient not wide enough not deep
enough you will not be able to boil it
down in an unintelligible
sense
and and not um just be repeating what
others have said like uh I can you know
I can memorize a whole essay I can
memorize I can be the master of
comparison I can read all the sutas got
all my phds in comparative studies so
when you say this I say oh yeah that's
another sutta that says that well that's
irrelevant I don't care what other sutas
say about that I care about the meaning
of this which I just said can you boil
down the meaning to me without resorting
to any other or any other thing that
somebody else said including the Buddha
himself can you in your own words boil
down the root of suffering that you
understood for yourself the freedom from
suffering the craving any aspect of the
Dharma describe
it and that's when you realize how
inadequate your own our own
idiosyncratic images and thinking is so
if you don't actually come out of that
level and recognize that no no no I need
to be able to convey this that it will
be the measure of the the strength of my
understanding you will remain in that
level and and perpetually continue
conflating um
pleasing uh theoretical fits and
abstractions and how it all Blends and
connections with wisdom and
understanding and that's not where it
is so it it kind of reminds me of like a
danger of
um like monastic life in a sense of
Hermits let's say people who go away and
just live by themselves that's could be
that's like one of the dangers cuz then
you get locked up in that what you just
said in your own
abstractions and you never actually
realized you can't actually convey this
you can't
even well I think that's also one of the
reasons it kind of translates to that
whole requirement of needing to have at
least the Right View before you should
go in like height and seclusion
that the describe to be able to contain
your mind and also to be able to know
where the emphasis is and should be and
obviously the benefit of
um being questioned and that is that
that cannot be stated uh um hard enough
really like uh did you pressed for
answers did you pressed for
clarification did you have people that
are able to do
that that's already sending you in the
right direction even if you don't
necessarily see it for
yourself and that's often you see that
in the sutas they would cross-examine
each other not like for the sake of some
impersonal debate but genuinely like how
do you understand this how do you how
about this how about that they would
then actually amplify their own
understanding and then those who believe
they understood things but haven't fully
but then asked the simple question and
he's just just fumbling just fumbling
for words just talking in these
abstractions that like you know by the
end of the sentence in makes no makes no
sense anymore so with cross examination
and interrogation they would realize if
obviously they're honest which
presumably there were back in the day
when you read that in the SAS they
realize oh yeah yeah I was lacking I was
and this actually is helpful now I know
that I'm not clear because if I were
clear well I would have I would have
said so I would have made it clear
certainly to another person who is
familiar with this that I don't have to
teach from scratch or something
everything about what budha said
beforehand and so on
so you need to you need to know that you
actually if you understood things you
should be able to to boil them down
condense them and explain them in very
simple language if you don't need to resort to
language if you don't need to resort to
a complex language in terms to explain
things you know your understanding is is
is decent and certainly along the right
lines there's always room for
improvement basically but if you can
only explain things by resorting to um
complex terminology that requires years
of study from your audence audence in
order to understand to it means like
well that's already quite um devoid of
practical application so yeah you can
use complex terms if you want if there
is a reason for it but you will also be
able to use simple and plain language
because these are pretty much not
complex truths that have many moving
Parts non- ownership impermanence
suffering um there's nothing complex
about it but there is a certain order to
it
that has to be done rightly so to see
these things and that can all be
explained in a very straightforward
language and the only reason a person
would not understand you then not be
it's not because of the word you used or
because the the complexity of your
descriptions it's because they refuse to
accept that truth of non- ownership and
anich and so on and they would not
understand what you're saying because of
that because of their mental attitude of
looking for faults and and and just
ignoring what you're saying because it's
too unpleasant to accept